Guide to the Vassar Family Papers, 1804-circa 1992
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Vassar Family Papers
1804-circa 1992
1804-1891
Vassar family
1 cubic foot (3 boxes, 1 OV folder)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Deeds, mortgages, bonds, insurance papers, agreements, wills, complaints, letters, accounts, cancelled checks, leases, and other items concerning estate and business matters of George Booth, James Booth, Charles Vassar, James Vassar, John Guy Vassar, and Matthew Vassar, Jr.
Biographical Note
The founder of Vassar College was Matthew Vassar. He was born to James and Ann Vassar on 29 April 1792 in East Dereham, Norfolk. He had eight siblings, including sisters Sophia, Maria, Jemima and Kezia; and brothers John Guy, Charles and James. John Guy Vassar had two sons: John Guy Vassar, Jr. and Matthew Vassar, Jr.
Matthew's sister, Maria, married George Booth. Their daughter was Lydia Booth, who was instrumental in Matthew's decision to found a college for women.
Chronology
29 Dec 1789 John Guy Vassar born in East Dereham, Norfolk, England, to James and Ann Vassar
29 Apr 1792 Matthew Vassar born
1796 James and Ann Vassar moved their family to the United States
1797 James and Ann purchased a farm in Dutchess County
10 Jan 1797 Charles Vassar born
1801 James and Ann sold the farm and moved to Poughkeepsie to start a brewery
22 Nov 1801 James Vassar, Jr. born
10 May 1811 The brewery burned to the ground, uninsured
11 May 1811 John Guy Vassar died examining the debris
1811 In his grief, James Vassar abandoned Poughkeepsie, and Matthew started a new brewery called M. Vassar and Co.
1832 John Guy Vassar, Jr. and Matthew Vassar, Jr. (John Guy Vassar's sons), became partners in the brewery
1853 Death of James Vassar, Jr.
1861 Vassar College founded
16 Sep 1861 Death of Charles Vassar
26 Sep 1865 Vassar College opened
23 June 1868 Death of Matthew Vassar
Scope and Content Note
Deeds, mortgages, bonds, insurance papers, agreements, wills, complaints, letters, accounts, cancelled checks, leases, and other items concerning estate and business matters of George Booth, James Booth, Charles Vassar, James Vassar, John Guy Vassar, and Matthew Vassar, Jr.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library without any additional restrictions.
Related Materials
Matthew Vassar Papers
Vassar College Realia Collection
Local History Collection at the Adriance Memorial Library, Poughkeepsien NY
Subject Headings
Names:
Booth, George, ca. 1768-1833; Booth, James; Vassar, Charles; Vassar, James; Vassar, John Guy, 1811-1888; Vassar, Matthew, 1792-1868
Subjects:
Baptists--New York (State)--Poughkeepsie; Women's colleges--New York (State)--Poughkeepsie; Family--New York (State)--Poughkeepsie; Decedents' estates--New York (State)--Dutchess County; Real property--New York (State)--Dutchess County
Places:
Dutchess County (N.Y.)--Commerce; Poughkeepsie (N.Y.)--Religious life and customs
VCL Categories:
Family; Local History; Religion
Encoding Information
Encoded by Elizabeth Clarke, February 2007. Last updated by Emma Gronbeck, June 2025.
Acquisition Information
Gift of various donors.
Container List
- Booth, George, 1802-1822 (Folder 1.1)
- Booth, George, 1804-1814; (8 items) (Folder 3.1)
- Booth, James, 1815, 1820, 1835; (3 items) (Folder 3.2)
- Vassar, Charles G. (Folder 2.11)
- Vassar, Helen H. — autograph (Folder 2.1)
- Vassar, James — "Indexed" bonds, deeds, leases and mortgages, 1797-1812 (Folder 1.2)
- Vassar, James — "Indexed" bonds, deeds, leases and mortgages, 1813-1831 (Folder 1.3)
- Vassar, James — "Indexed" bonds, deeds, leases and mortgages, 1804-1817; (23 items) (Folder 3.3)
- Vassar, James — Miscellaneous statements and notes, circa 1807-1852 (Folder 1.4)
- Vassar, Jessie, 1911 (Folder 1.5)
- Vassar, John Guy — Estate, circa 1889-1891 (Folder 1.6)
- Vassar, John Guy — Estate (Folder 1.7)
- Vassar, John Guy — Estate (Folder 1.8)
- Vassar, Matthew — Raymond biography and William Kelly letter, 1868 (Folder 2.2)
- Vassar, Matthew Jr. — Notes from diary taken by James M. Taylor (Folder 2.3)
- Vassar, Matthew Jr. — Correspondence regarding "Mr. Lyon's Will,", 1876-1879 (Folder 2.4)
- Vassar, Matthew Jr. — Miscellaneous, circa 1861-1889 (Folder 2.5)
- Vassar, Matthew Jr. — Unidentified letter [from the Booth collection?], 1846 Nov 4 (Folder 2.6)
- "Vassar Family of Norfolk Genealogy," compiled by Robin Lucas, 1978-1992 (Multiple Collections Box 2 (Oversize))
- Nestell property, 1835-1836 (Folder 2.7)
- Nestell property, 1825 (Folder 3.4)
- Poughkeepsie hotels, 1935, undated (Folder 2.8)
- Real Estate, Chemung County, N.Y., 1857 (Folder 2.9)
- Bonds, mortgages, and miscellaneous legal documents, 1812-1839 (Folder 2.10)
- Bonds, mortgages, and miscellaneous legal documents, 1808-1839; (11 items) (Folder 3.5)